Guide to the Wallace Fowlie Papers, 1911-1998 and undated RL.00411
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wallace Fowlie papers
1911-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fowlie, Wallace, 1908-1998
RL.00411
5 Linear Feet
Writer, critic, translator, and faculty member at Duke University specializing in modern French literature. The Wallace Fowlie Papers span the years 1911 to 1998 and consist mainly of correspondence sent to Fowlie, but also texts from Fowlie's personal library, publications on French literature authored by Fowlie, typescript and handwritten drafts by Fowlie, amd clippings pertaining to Fowlie's career. A significant portion of the correspondence comprises exchanges between Fowlie and Thomas and Kit Foster. These letters mainly address personal and family matters (health issues, vacations and meeting with mutual friends), but also cover projects Fowlie was working on, teaching positions accepted and rejected and class progress, and other matters of professional relevance. There is also a folder of correspondence with Fowlie, almost entirely in French, that was maintained by John M. Dunaway, a Romance Languages professor at Mercer College in Georgia. It includes a few color photographs. Other smaller amounts of correspondence come from Robert Heslen, a former student of Fowlie, and well-known writers/artists including René Char, Jean Cocteau, André Gide, Alexis Léger (Saint-Jean Perse), Marianne Moore, Anaïs Nin, and others, discussing literary matters and their writings and careers. There are letters from Fowlie to Walter Muther. A folder of general correspondence contains single letters from a variety of colleagues and friends. Selections from Fowlie's library are sorted into works and translations by Fowlie, and works he used privately or for his own research.
516 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Wallace Fowlie Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1981-2007, 2011, 2015 and 2018.
Includes Accessions: 2015-0128, 2015-0132, 2018-0095
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1908, Nov. 8 Wallace Fowlie born in Brookline, Massachussetts
1936 Received Doctorate from Harvard University
1943 Publication of Clowns and Angels: Studies in French Literature
1946 Rimbaud, the Myth of Childhood published
1951 Pantomime: A Journal of Rehearsals published
1953 Publication of Rimbaud's Illuminations
1964 Fowlie appointed to faculty at Duke University
1965 Publication of André Gide: His Life and Art
1966 Publication of Rimbaud (Complete Works) and Jean Cocteau: The History of a Poet's Age
1977 Duke Press published A Journal of Rehearsals, a revision and updating of the earlier 1951 autobiography, Pantomime: A Journal of Rehearsals
1983 Aubade: A Teacher's Notebook published
1984-1985 Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholar at nine universities and colleges
1987 Sites: A Third Memoir published
1990 Memory: A Fourth Memoir published
1990 Worked as consultant on Oliver Stone's film The Doors
1994 Publication of Rimbaud and Jim Morrison: The Rebel as Poet
1998, August 16 Died in Durham, North Carolina
Collection Overview
The Wallace Fowlie Papers span the years 1911 to 1998 and consist mainly of correspondence sent to Fowlie, but also texts from Fowlie's personal library, publications on French literature authored by Fowlie, typescript and handwritten drafts by Fowlie, amd clippings pertaining to Fowlie's career. A significant portion of the correspondence comprises exchanges between Fowlie and Thomas and Kit Foster. These letters mainly address personal and family matters (health issues, vacations and meeting with mutual friends), but also cover projects Fowlie was working on, teaching positions accepted and rejected and class progress, and other matters of professional relevance. There is also a folder of correspondence with Fowlie, almost entirely in French, that was maintained by John M. Dunaway, a Romance Languages professor at Mercer College in Georgia. It includes a few color photographs. Other smaller amounts of correspondence come from Robert Heslen, a former student of Fowlie, and well-known writers/artists including René Char, Jean Cocteau, André Gide, Alexis Léger (Saint-Jean Perse), Marianne Moore, Anaïs Nin, and others, discussing literary matters and their writings and careers. There are letters from Fowlie to Walter Muther. A folder of general correspondence contains single letters from a variety of colleagues and friends. Selections from Fowlie's library are sorted into works and translations by Fowlie, and works he used privately or for his own research.
Clippings (information artifacts); French literature; French poetry; Color photographs; Authors, American -- 20th century; French language -- 20th century; College teachers -- United States; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Nin, Anaïs, 1903-1977; Foster, Thomas; Gide, André, 1869-1951; Char, René, 1907-1988; Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963; Dunaway, John M., 1945-; Fowlie, Wallace, 1908-1998
- Correspondence, 1937-1998 and undated, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Chiefly consists of exchanges between Wallace Fowlie and well-known writers and friends. With the exception of the Foster, Heslen, and Muther correspondence, which contain letters from Fowlie, the bulk of the items are from correspondents writing to Fowlie. Substantial groups of correpondence from individuals have been foldered separately. Smaller amounts of one to four letters are housed in General Correspondence; correspondents include Alain Bosquet, Kenneth Burke, René Char, Edouard Dermit (the adopted son of Jean Cocteau), André Gide, Marianne Moore, Jean Renard, and others. Arranged in chronological order within folders, with the exception of General Correspondence, which is alphabetical by last name.
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1951-1963 (Box 1)
  - Dunaway, John M., 1965-1998 and undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - France, Erik, 1988-1993 and undated (Box 5)
    Also includes two books by Wallace (Rimbaud and Jim Morrison; Dante Today) with inscription to Erik France, dated August 1994 and March 1994.
  - Foster, Thomas and Kit, 1945-1996 and undated, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Heslen, Robert, 1947-1957 and undated (Box 1)
  - Léger, Alexis, 1951-1965 and undated (Box 2)
  - Muther, Walter, 1937-1953 (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Also contains a copy of Sleep of the Pigeon (1948), which Fowlie dedicated to Muther.
  - Nin, Anaïs, 1945-1966 and undated (Box 2)
  - General correspondence, 1939-1970 and undated (Box 2)
  - General correspondence, 1968, 1991, 1993 and undated (Box 5)
- Printed Material Series, 1953-1979 and undated, 2 folders
  - Printed material (Box 2)
    Contains various printed materials, including clippings, a publisher's catalog, writers' conference program, newsletter, project description, and a bibliography that was associated with correspondence to and from Thomas and Kit Foster. The clippings consist of newspaper and newsletter articles about Fowlie, some in interview format, that address his past and contemporary perspectives on literature and academia.
  - Printed material (Box 5)
    Contains various printed materials, including an issue of The New Yorker (July 27, 1998), a part of a book sleeve from a book by Iris Murdoch, several newspaper articles, obituaries, and book reviews on Murdoch as well as a book review by Murdoch from The New York Review (March 1993), an article on Saint Miller's correspondence with Wallace Fowlie, an article on Marcel Proust, one on Jim Morrison and The Doors, and the article "Why Our Politics Needs More Poets" by Erica Jong
- Writings, 1949-1977 and undated, 7 folders
  Consists of a small assortment of drafts and published versions of literary and biographical writings of Wallace Fowlie.
  - Journal of Rehearsals (typed draft with corrections), 1977, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Literary essays by Fowlie separated from R. Heslen correspondence, 1950, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Literary essays and a translation by Fowlie separated from Thomas and Kit Foster correspondence, 1949, 1952, 1955, and undated (Box 2)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 2)
    Consists of two spiral-bound notebooks containing Fowlie's hand-written drafts of literary essays.
- Books from Fowlie's personal library, 1911-1997; 1
  This series includes books from Wallace Fowlie's private library as well as some books Fowlie gave to others as gifts. Fowlie's own scholarship is represented in the first subseries, which contains works written or edited by Fowlie as well as a number of his translations of French-language literature (e.g. works on Arthur Rimbaud, Paul Claudel, Baudelaire) as well as a reading of Dante's Inferno. The second subseries contains Fowlie's personal copies of French (e.g. Marcel Proust, Georges Simenon), Italian (e.g. Dante), American (e.g. Thomas Wolfe, Edmund Fuller, T. S. Eliot), English (Shakespeare), and Irish (Iris Murdoch, James Joyce) literature in French and English as well as scholarship on French- and English-language literature by various authors. Many of the books include inscriptions and notes by Fowlie as well as laid-in letters, postcards, book reviews, clipped magazine, and newspaper articles.
  - Scholarship, Editions, and Translations by Fowlie, 1950-1997; 1
    - Rimbaud e Jim Morrison. Il poeta come ribelle. Traduzione di Elena Rossi (Milan: Il Saggiatore), 1997 (Box 3)
      Includes inscription by Fowlie on title page
    - Paul Claudel. Studies in Modern European Literature and Thought (London: Bowes Bowes), 1957 (Box 3)
      Includes laid-in newspaper article on Rimbaud
    - The French Critic 1549-1967 (Carbondale and Edwardsville: Southern Illinois University Press; London-Amsterdam: Feffer Simons, Inc.), 1968 (Box 3)
      Includes some notes and laid-in newspaper articles (mainly reviews of the book) and letters to the author
    - Rimbaud. A Critical Study (Chicago London: The University of Chicago Press), 1966 (Box 3)
    - Rimbaud. Complete Works, Selected Letters (French-English). Introduction, Prose Translations and Notes by Wallace Fowlie (Chicago London: The University of Chicago Press), 1966 (Box 3)
      Includes laid-in review of the book
    - A Reading of Dante's Inferno (Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press), 1981 (Box 3)
      Includes laid-in photographs, postcard, and letter
    - Age of Surrealism (New York: The Swallow Press and William Morrow and Co., Inc.), 1950 (Box 3)
      Includes inscription by Fowlie
    - Five Classic French Plays. Editted and Translated by Wallace Fowlie (Mineola, New York: Dover Publications, Inc.), 1962 (Box 3)
    - Modern French Poets. Selections with Translations. A Dual-Language Boook. Edited by Wallace Fowlie (New York: Dover Publications, Inc.), 1955 (Box 3)
    - Baudelaire, Charles. Flowers of Evel and Other Works. Les Fleurs du mal et oeuvres choisies. A Dual-Language Book. Selections from Baudelaire's poetry, critical writings, journals, and letters, in the original French and a new English translation. Edited and translated by Wallace Fowlie (New York: Dover Publications, Inc.), 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      Includes letter and postcard
    - French Stories. Contes Francais. A Dual-Language Book. Ten short stories by Voltaire, Balzac, Gide, Camus and others in the original French and a new English translation. Edited by Wallace Fowlie (New York: Dover Publications, Inc.), 1960/1988 (Box 3)
    - St.-John Perse. Seamarks. Bilingual Edition. Harper Torchbooks/The Bollingen Library. Translation by Wallace Fowlie (New York: Harper Brothers), 1958/1961 (Box 3)
      Includes notes and special print of article by Walter A. Strauss
    - Baudelaire, Charles. Selected Poems from "Flowers of Evil." Selected ans Translated by Wallace Fowlie. Dover Thrift Editions (New York: Dover Publications, Inc.), 1963-1964/1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - English and Non-English Literature and Scholarship, 1911-1995; 2
    - Proust, Marcel. Remembrance of Things Past. The definitive French Pleiade edition translated by C. K. Scott Moncrieff and Terence Kilmartin (New York: Vintage Books), 1981-1982; 3 Volumes (Box 3)
      Includes notes
    - Le Monde de Proust. Photographies de Paul Nadar (Paris: Editions CNMHS), 1991 (Box 3)
      Includes inscription for Fowlie
    - Simenon, Georges. La Premiere Enquete de Maigret (1913) (Paris: Presses da la Cite), 1990 (Box 3)
    - Simenon, Georges. Maigret et le Marchand de vin (Pairs: Presses de la Cite), 1971 (Box 3)
    - Simenon, Georges. Maigret et l'Homme tout seul (Paris: Presses de la Cite), 1972 (Box 3)
    - Simenon, Georges. Maigret voyage (Paris: Presses de la Cite), 1957 (Box 3)
    - Simenon, Georges. La Maison du canal (Paris: Presses de la Cite), 1976 (Box 3)
    - Maritain, Raissa. Les Grandes Amities. Souvernirs (New York, N. Y.: Editions de la Maison Francaise, Inc.), 1940-1941 (Box 3)
      Includes notes and laid-in newspaper article
    - Anonymous, Henriette Psichari. 18 octobre 1965 (no place of publication and publisher), no publication date (Box 3)
      Includes laid-in newspaper article
    - Anonymous, Henriette Psichari (no place of publication and publisher), 1973 (Box 3)
    - Psichari, Henriette. La Priere sur l'acropole et ses mysteres (Paris: Editions du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique), 1956 (Box 3)
      Includes inscription by Psichari on title page, notes, photographs, a telegram, and clipped articles
    - Gadoffre, Gilbert. Ronsard par lui-meme. "Ecrivains de toujours" aux editions du seuil (no place of publication: Collections Microcosme), 1960 (Box 3)
      Includes an inscription for Fowlie and notes
    - Millan, Gordon. A Throw of the Dice. The Life of Stephane Mallarme (New York: Farrar Straus Giroux), 1994 (Box 3)
      Includes letters and article clippings
    - Peyre, Henri. French Novelists of Today (New York: Oxford University Press), 1955/1967 (Box 4)
      Includes inscription, notes, reviews of the book, and articles on Peyre
    - Knapp, Bettina L. Jean Cocteau. Updated Edition. Twayne's World Authors Series. French Literature (Boston: Twayne Publishers), 1989 (Box 4)
      Includes notes, book reviews on Fowlies's "Jean Cocteau: The History of a Poet's Age," letters, and article clippings
    - Peters, Arthur King. Jean Cocteau and His World. An Illustrated Biography (New York-Paris: The Vendome Press), 1986 (Box 4)
      Includes inscription for Fowlie and newspaper article clipping with personal note to Fowlie
    - Murdoch, Iris. The Nice and the Good (New York: Penguin Books), 1978 (Box 4)
    - Murdoch, Iris. The Flight From the Enchanter. A Story of Love and Power (New York: Penguin Books), 1962 (Box 4)
      Includes notes and photographs of Murdoch
    - Murdoch, Iris. The Good Apprentice (New York: Penguin Books), 1987 (Box 4)
    - Murdoch, Iris. An Accidental Man (New York: Viking Press), 1971 (Box 4)
    - Joyce, James. A Portrait of the Artist As a Young Man. The Modern Library of the World's Best Books (New York: Random House), 1928 (Box 4)
    - Joyce, James. Ulysses. The Modern Library of the World's Best Books (New York: Random House), 1961 (Box 4)
      Icludes notes, a postcard, and clipped articles
    - The Complete Works of William Shakespeare. Edited by William George Clark and William Aldis Wright (New York: Cumberland Publishing Company), 1911 (Box 4)
    - Fuller, Edmund. Brothers Divided (New York-Indianapolis: The Bobbs-Merrill Company, Inc.), 1951 (Box 4)
      Includes inscription for Fowlie and notes
    - Fuller, Edmund. A Star Pointed North (New York and London: Harper Brothers Publishers), 1946 (Box 4)
      Includes inscription for Fowlie, notes, and envelope with article clippings on Fuller
    - Fuller, Edmund. The Corridor (New York: Random House), 1963 (Box 4)
      Includes Fuller's autograph and inscription for Fowlie
    - Warren, Austin. Becoming What One Is (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press), 1995 (Box 4)
      Includes inscription for Wallace, notes, photocopies of selected pages, letters, a postcard, and a clipped newspaper article
    - Wolfe, Thomas. The Hills Beyond (Chicago: Elephant Paperbacks), 1991 (Box 4)
      Includes a letter to Fowlie
    - Eliot, T. S. Collected Poems 1909-1935 (New York: Harcourt, Brace and Company), 1936 (Box 4)
      Includes notes, a letter to Fowlie, and clipped article on Eliot
    - Bloom, Allan. Giants and Dwarfs. Essays: 1960-1990 (Advance Uncorrected Reader's Proof from Simon and Schuster, New York) (Box 5)
    - Townsend, Davis. Weary Feet, Rested Souls. A Guided History of the Civil Rights Movement (New York: W. W. Norton Company, Inc.), 1998 (Box 5)
      Includes inscription for Fowlie, review of the book, and letters
    - The Divine Comedy of Dante Alighieri. Inferno. A Verse Translation by Allen Mandelbaum (New York-Toronto-London-Sydney-Auckland: Bantam Books), 1980 (Box 5)
    - Alighieri, Dante. Inferno. Translated into English verse, with notes and an introduction by Elio Zappulla (New York: Pantheon Books), 1998 (Box 5)
      Includes inscription and a letter by the publisher to Fowlie
    - The Dore Illustrations for Dante's Divine Comedy. 136 Plates by Gustave Dore (New York: Dover Publications, Inc.), 1976 (Box 5)
      Includes flyers for several events titled "Inferno"
    - Cervigni, Dino S. Dante's Lucifer: The Denial of the Word (excerpt from "Lectura Dantis. A forum for Dante research and interpretation), 1988, Fall (Box 5)
    - Bonechi, Edoardo. Florence. A Complete Guide For Visiting the City (Florence: Bonechi Edizioni "Il Turismo"), 1972 (Box 5)
      Includes inscription, notes, and a clipped article on Dante
    - Les Geants de la litterature mondiale. Dante Alighieri (Paris: Periodique Match), 1970 (Box 5)
- Teaching Material Series, 1987 and undated
  General Physical Description note
  1 folder
  - Teaching material (Box 5)
    Includes lecture notes on "T. S. Eliot: An Introduction to His Career and Achievements" and on Rimbaud and Morrison; lecture announcements for "Collecting Drawings of Cocteau, Picasso, Matisse, and Henry Miller" and "Jim Morrison and Rimbaud. The Rebel as Artist;" and a syllabus for a course on Proust syllabus.
- AV and Photographs Series, 1994 and undated
  - Photographs (Box 5)
    Contains four photographs of Fowlie and others.
  - One cassette tape labeled "Les Fleurs Du Mal, a ballet by ML Pinsky. Dedicated to Wallace Fowlie, 1994." (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL-00411-CS-0001)